这个巨大的太阳能工厂建在遥远的亚利桑那沙漠
This vast solar power plant being built in the remote Arizona desert
是史上最大的经济救援措施之一
is part of the biggest economic rescue effort in history.
这些措施的实施成本巨大
While the cost of action will be great,
但不实施的成本将更为巨大
I can assure you that the cost of inaction will be far greater.
由于经济仍处在疲软期
With the economy still struggling,
美国政府拟投资7500亿美元
the American government is shelling out three-quarters of a trillion dollars
带动国家走出困境
to try to haul the country out of trouble.
英国政府为了加速发展也投资了数十亿
And in Britain, billions are being spent to accelerate growth,
尽管其决心削减政府支出
even by a government determined to cut borrowing.
这是解决问题的正确方法么?
Is this really the right road to take?
2008年经济危机后  全球经济体似乎都出现了现金短缺
After the crash in 2008, the world seemed to be running out of cash.
但是各国政府并没有削减支出  反而在继续透支他们没有的现金
But rather than cut back,governments spent huge amounts of money they didn¹t have.
他们为什么要这么做?
Why on earth would they do that?
一切都可以归结为这个人的超凡理念
It¹s all goes back to the extraordinary ideas of this man,
英国经济学家-梅纳德·凯恩斯
the British economist John Maynard Keynes.
简而言之  他改变了世界
Quite simply, he changed the world.
我认为他是20世纪最伟大的人物之一
I think it is true that he¹s one of the great figures of the 20th century
即使在21世纪的很多方面  他也是伟人之一
and in many ways of the 21st century.
凯恩斯认为资本主义本身是完善的
Keynes thought capitalism was brilliant.
但是如果任其发展  也可能导致严重不良后果
But left to its own devices, it could also go seriously wrong.
政府有责任将经济拉回正道
It was up to governments to step in to get the economy back on track.
他具有白厅 威斯敏斯特以及剑桥人的典型特征  非常自信
He was the archetypal man in Whitehall, Westminster or Cambridge who thought he knew best.
今天  凯恩斯成为了前所未有的关注焦点和争议中心
Keynes has never been more relevant or controversial than he is today.
因为  自20世纪30年代以来首次出现了
Because for the first time since the 1930s,
他当时极力想解决的问题
the problems he was grappling with then...
银行破产  国际经济危机
bank failures, international crises,
长期经济衰退的可能性-我们今天也面临着
the possibility of a long economic slump - we¹re facing, too.
这个系列中  我将讲述三个伟人的生活及思想
In this series, I¹ll tell you about the lives and thoughts of three extraordinary men
他们有着截然不同的观点
with radically different views.
卡尔·马克思  弗雷德里希·哈耶克  以及今晚的梅纳德·凯恩斯
Karl Marx, Friedrich Hayek and, tonight, Keynes.
他们都看到了货币不断增长的魔力
They all saw that taming the growing power of money
如何掌控则是现代世界的最大挑战
was the crucial challenge for the modern world.
这三位都是思想上的巨人
All three were intellectual giants
他们的观点是形成当今世界的隐性推动力
whose ideas have been a hidden force shaping world events,
也改变了我们每个人的生活
changing the lives of every one of us.
但是我认为  就算今天  他们也能告诉我们一些特别的东西
But I think they have something special to tell us right now,
因为他们比其他任何人更能教会我们货币的巨大威力
because they, more than anyone, taught us the awesome power of money,
市场和资本带来的好处以及可能引发的大麻烦
the good that markets and capitalism could do and the enormous trouble they could cause.
我认为他们非常清楚我们正在经历什么
I think they¹d know exactly what we¹ve been going through.
我想知道  他们是否能带领我们找到出路?
I want to know, can they help us find a way out?
货币大师-凯恩斯
=========记录片之家倾情奉献=========
本字幕仅供学习交流  严禁用于商业用途 翻译:HELLO  校对:LSCAROLLI
英格兰西北寂静的山岭中
The quiet hills of north-west England.
一个偶然的机会  我用行动体验了经济学
For me, a chance to experience economics in action.
在游览坎布里亚郡时  我试着参加了拉力赛
I¹m getting to try out rally cars competing in the Tour of Cumbria.
赛事赞助商  倍耐力得到了政府24亿资金的一部分
The sponsors, Pirelli, are getting a slice of the government¹s £2.4 billion fund
用于帮助地方经济增长和就业增长
to help regional growth and employment.
他们想向我展示该公司到底是做什么的
They want to show me what the company¹s really all about.
倍耐力是全球最大的轮胎制造商之一
Pirelli is one of the world¹s biggest tyre makers.
其生产基地位于英国已经将近一个世纪
It¹s been manufacturing in Britain for almost a century.
他想发展一些高端产品  并加强研发
It wants to develop some of its top ranges and beef up research and development.
太棒了  简直太棒了
Brilliant. Absolutely brilliant.
但其成效并不尽如人意
But the sums hadn¹t been adding up.
这个工厂是卡莱尔市最大的雇主之一
This factory is one of Carlisle¹s biggest employers.
这儿有大约750个工人  一天生产1万个轮胎
There are about 750 workers here, producing 10,000 tyres a day.
不久前  人们担心工厂为了降低成本会将生产转移至海外
Not so long ago, people worried the company would shift production overseas to cut costs.
200万磅的政府补偿帮助让倍耐力留在了英国
A £2 million government grant has persuaded Pirelli to invest in Britain instead.
当我们有一项大投资时
When we have a major investment, the confidence in people
民众支出其薪酬的意愿加强
to spend their wages is increased.
当地经济将从中受益
And the local economy benefits.
不仅仅是倍耐力的雇员
And it's not only Pirelli employees.
还有依靠该工厂的数百个供应商和承包商
We have hundreds of suppliers and contractors who depend on this factory
当倍耐力支出增加时  他们也从中受益
and they benefit also when Pirelli increases its spend.
而他们也会导致货币回流至当地经济
And also they recycle that money into the local economy.
听上去很神奇...
It might seem surprising...
政府在担心不断攀升的国家债务时  投向私人企业的援助款
a handout to a private company, when the government's so worried about the mounting national debt,
至今已超过1万亿英镑
now more than a trillion pounds.
但凯恩斯洞若观火
But Keynes was quite clear.
"有些时候我们需要介入让资本主义为我们服务
There are times when we need to step in to make capitalism work for us,
哪怕是正在花我们没有的钱"
even when that means spending money we don¹t have.
凯恩斯的意思是  有可能得让政府
What Keynes said was that it was possible for government
介入以使市场运作得更好
to come in and make markets work better.
有一种说法经常被提起  凯恩斯从资本家手中救出了资本主义
One way that it¹s often put is that Keynes saved capitalism from the capitalists.
然而凯恩斯的批评者认为  是政府的错误才导致了问题
Though for Keynes¹ critics, it¹s mistakes by governments that really cause the trouble.
当我们发现经济严重失衡的事例时
When we find instances of economies being seriously knocked out of equilibrium,
它通常是政府错误政策的后果
it¹s generally been as a result of government policy mistakes.
但凯恩斯并未给出有说服力的论据
But Keynes didn¹t really make a convincing case
来说明即使当经济失衡时
that even when an economy was knocked out of equilibrium,
政府介入行为将比任由经济自行改善要做得更好
that government action could do better than allowing the economy to essentially mend itself.
所以凯恩斯若非经济的救世主
So Keynes was either an economic saviour,
就是把我们引向歧途的人
or the man who led us all astray.
但无可争议的是  他改变了我们的世界
But there¹s no argument that he changed our world
以及我们看待世界的方法
and the way we think about it.
80年前  他是争议的焦点  如今他又成为了争议的焦点
He was at the centre of the debate 80 years ago and he¹s back there again today.
我们肩上的重担没有了...
A great weight is lifted from us...
这是仅存的凯恩斯的演讲资料
This is the only known film of Keynes speaking.
汇率不会大幅下降
There's no danger of the exchange falling too far.
生活成本也不会大幅上升
There's no danger of a serious rise in the cost of living.
这是经济学的一个节目  关于如何共享世界资源
It's a broadcast about economics, how to share out the world's resources.
同时  英国贸易...
Meanwhile, British trade...
对凯恩斯来说  这不是干巴巴的科学
But for Keynes, this was no dry science.
而是如何将世界变得更好
It was about changing the world for the better.
如果我们回顾那些于20世纪作出了重大贡献的英国人
I think if we're looking at Britons who made a real difference in the 20th century,
最明显的莫过于温斯顿·丘吉尔
the most obvious name would be Winston Churchill.
紧随其后的就是梅纳德·凯恩斯
John Maynard Keynes is really not far behind.
凯恩斯在伦敦的这个房子里过了许多年
Keynes spent years in this house in London,
形成的观点影响了20世纪的一些重大事件
developing ideas that helped shape some of the most important events of the past century,
帮助从大萧条中拯救资本主义  资助了反纳粹的战争
helping to save capitalism from the Great Depression, funding the war against the Nazis,
建立了战后新经济秩序
and building a new post-war economic order
为其后几十年的经济发展与繁荣铺平了道路
that helped pave the way for decades of growth and rising prosperity.
用现代观点看  凯恩斯最非凡的地方在于他的切入点
What¹s really extraordinary about Keynes from a modern perspective was his access.
尽管他的生活  特别是他的思想没有循规蹈矩
Despite being so unconventional in his life and especially in his views,
他得以使位高权重者倾听
he had the ear of anyone who mattered.
总统和总理都愿意听他要说的话
Presidents and Prime Ministers all listened to what he had to say.
尽管只在他死后  他的建议才真正付诸实施
Though it was only after his death that everyone started taking his advice.
我1965年申请入学
I applied to university in 1965,
整个学术氛围  不仅是经济学  也包括政治学
and the whole intellectual climate, not just in economics but politics,
都受到凯恩斯已然解决了经济问题这一观念之推动
was driven by the idea that Keynes had solved the economic problem.
至60年代后期  凯恩斯的观点已经整合进了几乎所有的西方经济中
By the late 1960s, Keynes' ideas were built into the fabric of pretty much every western economy.
但是他似乎无法回答70年代的高通胀的问题
But he didn¹t seem to have an answer to the high inflation of the 1970s.
自那以后  凯恩斯主义的微调论开始过时
After that, Keynesian fine-tuning was out
自由市场主义逐渐占据主导地位
and free-market ideas gradually took over.
但当2008年全球经济陷入困境时  凯恩斯又回来了
But when the world got into serious bother in 2008, Keynes was back.
思想推动世界  向左还是向右  变好或变坏
It's ideas that mobilise the world, on right and left, good and bad.
我认为  凯恩斯的整套思想
And Keynes was the author of, in MY judgment,
是思考当今资本主义的方法中最好的
the best suite of ideas about how to think about capitalism that there's been.
如果你认为方法有用  那么他就有用
And if you think that counts, then he counts.
那么这些长时间主导了经济社会的伟大思想是什么
So what are these great ideas that have dominated our economic landscape for so long
它们又是从哪里发展起来的?
and where exactly did they come from?
凯恩斯生于1883年  英帝国的鼎盛时期
Keynes was born at the height of the British Empire, in 1883,
中产阶级的父母送他去了伊顿和剑桥
to middle-class parents who sent him to Eton and Cambridge.
一切看上去很传统
So far, so conventional.
但在大学里  他迷上了一个不传统的团体  布鲁姆斯伯里帮
But at university he fell in with a very unconventional crowd, the Bloomsbury Set.
作为一个年轻人  他有大量时间是在他们位于苏塞克斯
As a young man, he spent a lot of time here at their country retreat,
查尔斯顿的乡间别墅度过的
Charleston in Sussex.
这是一个由艺术家 作家还有一个经济学家构成的社团
It was a kind of commune for artists and writers and the one economist.
他们认为自己很特别
They did see themselves as very different.
他们青睐的是那不可名状的概念-波希米亚式
They were tinged by that rather indefinable concept, bohemian.
他们领先于时代  他们的性观念超前
They were very ahead of their time. They were pioneers about sexual behaviour.
他们是政治领域的先行者
They were pioneers on a political front.
他们在很多美学领域也是先行者
They were pioneers in many aesthetic fields,
比如文学  比如艺术
in writing and in the arts.
布鲁姆斯伯里帮允许他打破成规
The Bloomsbury group allowed him to step outside of the box
去思考一些不曾被思考的问题
and to think the unthinkable.
而他广阔的知识领域
And that breadth of intellect that he had
让他有信心义无反顾地挑战任何难题
allowed him to leap off cliffs with a confidence that there was no bottom.
凯恩斯一生都热爱文化
Keynes immersed himself in the cultural world all his life,
收集着绘画 图书  甚至资助在这里的剑桥艺术学院
collecting paintings, fine books, even founding the Arts Theatre here in Cambridge.
或许这并非巧合  一个兴趣如此广泛的人
Perhaps it¹s no coincidence that a man with such wide-ranging interests
就应该有远见来发展出关于经济学的全新方法
should have the vision to develop a radically new approach to economics,
凯恩斯主义  是对如今政府干预经济的简称
Keynesianism, shorthand today for government efforts to control the economy.
将近130年前  凯恩斯诞生在一个自信的年代
Keynes was born, nearly 130 years ago, into a confident age.
科学大步向前
Science had been marching forward in medicine, in engineering,
医学 工程学在不断拓展人类的极限
every year extending what was humanly possible.
但是有一个领域  科学甚至尚未涉足..
But there was one domain where science had barely begun...
经济学 - 货币和市场的世界
economics, the world of money and markets.
如果我们能够掌控资本主义  便可决定自己的命运
If we could tame capitalism, we could really shape our destiny.
这是凯恩斯的信念
Keynes fundamentally believed that.
但是他也知道  也许比他的部分追随者更清楚地知道
But he also understood, maybe better than some of his followers,
这将会面临多大的困难
just how difficult that was going to be.
希腊人大为光火地认为国家银根紧缩是被他们的欧洲邻居所强加的
Greek fury at the austerity they feel has been imposed on them by their European neighbours.
在凯恩斯看来  这可能有点熟悉
For Keynes, this might feel a bit familiar.
他亲眼目睹了强国将经济条款强加于弱国身上
He saw at first-hand the disaster that can come from stronger countries
会带来的恶果
dictating economic terms to the weak.
那也正促使他形成了首个重要理论
That helped him form his first big idea.
在一个高度关联的世界  在求助于邻国的同时还得依靠自己
In an interconnected world, when you beggar your neighbour you might well beggar yourself.
这个观点深受第一次世界大战所带来的恐惧之影响
It was an idea forged by the horrors of World War I.
忠实于布鲁姆斯伯里帮的价值观
True to his Bloomsbury values,
凯恩斯不想参战
Keynes didn¹t want to fight in the war.
但是他愿意用他的经济学才华来资助战争
But he was willing to use his economic brilliance to help finance it.
凯恩斯在财政部的工作是帮助盟国的其他国家从美国获得贷款
Keynes' job at the Treasury was to help channel loans from America to other countries in the alliance.
这个工作让他意识到全球经济已是如何地紧密相连
His time here brought home to him how integrated the global economy had become.
独善其身是不可能的
Isolation just wasn¹t an option.
全体人类的经济命运
The economic fate of entire populations
可能取决于千里  甚至万里以外的事件
might come to depend on events hundreds, even thousands, of miles away.
战争刚结束  凯恩斯便见证了对战败德国的憎恨是如何
Once the war was over, Keynes could see how hatred of the defeated Germans
可能导致战胜国犯下严重的错误
might lead the victors to make a terrible mistake.
一战尾声阶段  公众对于德国的敌意是相当显而易见的
At the end of the First World War there was a great deal of obviously public hostility towards Germany.
无论对生者还是死者  这都是一场恐怖的战争
It had been a disastrous war both in terms of lives and casualties,
经济上也是
but economically, too.
我相信当时有强烈的意愿要求德国必须进行赔偿
I think there was quite a strong feeling that Germany must be made to pay.
在凡尔赛宫签订了和平协议
At the Palace of Versailles, where the peace treaty was signed,
英国首相劳埃德·乔治和他法国及美国的盟友玩味着他们的胜利
British Prime Minister Lloyd George and his French and American allies relished their victory.
凯恩斯是英国代表团的一员  但是与他的建议相左
Keynes was a member of the British delegation here but, against his advice,
德国被要求赔偿由于战争而对各国造成的损害和苦难
Germany was ordered to pay everyone¹s bills for the damage and suffering caused by the war.
德国如何承担得起这笔债?
How could Germany afford to repay that debt?
得需要一个能产生货币和财富的正常经济
You need an economy that is running to produce money and wealth.
然后才能偿还债务
And then you can repay.
你不能什么都没有就偿债
You cannot repay out of nothing.
凯恩斯很愤怒  他辞去了财政部的工作
Keynes was so outraged that he resigned from the Treasury
返回查尔斯顿的住所
and retreated to his room in Charleston
写下了他的第一部主要作品"和平的经济后果"
to write his first major book, ªThe Economic Consequences of the Peaceº.
写得非常精辟  成为了畅销书
Brilliantly written, it became a best seller,
尽管有人说  他对德国的同情应该被授予铁十字勋章
though some said, with his sympathy for the Germans, he should be awarded an Iron Cross.
他说  "如果我们的目标旨在令中欧贫困
He says, "If we aim deliberately at the impoverishment of Central Europe,
我敢预言, 复仇将用不会停止"
"vengeance, I dare predict, will not limp."
但对我来说  关键点在于
But the key point for me is,
他不仅仅认为停战协议既不道德又不公平  而且认为它很愚蠢
he didn¹t just think it was immoral, the treaty, or unfair, he thought it was stupid.
他认为一个绝望的德国将不会维持欧洲的和平
He thought a desperate Germany wasn¹t going to keep the peace in Europe,
必然也不会为其繁荣做出贡献
and it certainly wasn¹t going to contribute to prosperity.
它不会从英国进口产品  帮助英国战后复苏
It wasn¹t going to buy goods from Britain and help Britain recover from the war.
纵观他的一生  他以各种方式反复提及
Something he kept coming back to one way or another throughout his life...
我们都是紧密相连的
we¹re all in it together.
凡尔赛合约迫使欧洲的一个大国跪下了
The Versailles Treaty brought one of the great powers of Europe to its knees.
正如凯恩斯所预计的  德国经济陷入混乱
As Keynes predicted, the German economy descended into chaos.
他们的债务如此之大  以至于他们不断印制钞票用于还债
Their debts were so impossibly large, they ended up printing the money to pay the bills
而这迅速导致了高通胀和完全失去价值的货币
which quickly led to hyperinflation and a thoroughly worthless currency.
高通胀不仅摧毁了经济
Hyperinflation didn¹t just destroy the economy.
也摧毁了德国社会的基础 - 民众的希望
It destroyed the fabric of German society, people¹s hopes, too.
有故事说  有人取出了他们的全部积蓄
There are stories about people taking out all of their savings
买了一枚用于自杀遗书上的邮票
to buy a single postage stamp for a suicide letter.
当凯恩斯警告凡尔赛合约将导致灾难性后果时
When Keynes warned that the Versailles Treaty would bring a catastrophe here,
甚至他的推崇者都认为他过于夸张
even his admirers might have thought he was exaggerating.
但很快他们就不这么认为了
But they didn¹t think that for long.
胜利万岁! 胜利万岁!
Sieg Heil! Sieg Heil!
就在凡尔赛合约签订的14年后  希特勒上台
Just 14 years after the Treaty of Versailles, Hitler came to power.
二战转眼即至
World War II wasn't far away.
正如凯恩斯所预测的  将经济利害关系弄错的代价是惨痛的
As Keynes had predicted, the price of getting economic relations wrong was calamity.
凯恩斯预见过赔款过于沉重  应该进行调整
Keynes foresaw that the reparations were too onerous, would have to be adjusted
那就相当于埋下导致下一次欧洲混乱的种子
and that actually you were laying the seeds of the next European conflagration.
他认为那是极其短视的  他是对的
He thought it was unbelievably short-sighted. He was right.
凯恩斯会怎么看今天的欧洲?
So what would Keynes make of Europe today?
他将再次看到强国对弱国的经济政策指手画脚
Well, once again he might see strong countries dictating economic terms to the weak,
尽管这一次是像德国这样的强国
though this time it's strong countries like Germany itself
主张危机重重的国家  如希腊
insisting that crisis-ridden nations, like Greece,
应签署严厉的削减预算条款以换取紧急援助
sign up to tough budget cuts in exchange for emergency loans.
报纸已经展示了由于经济危机所带来的恶劣程度
The newspapers show the depth of ill will that¹s built up as a result of the crisis.
德国人称希腊为毫无用处的乞丐
You¹ve got the Germans talking about the Greeks as no-good scroungers.
而在希腊  再也不禁止将德国领导人比作纳粹了
But in Greece, well, there¹s no more taboo any more about comparing German leaders to Nazis.
凯恩斯也许会说他们正重蹈那场错误战争的覆辙
But Keynes might say they were harking back to the wrong war.
讽刺的是  加诸希腊的苛刻条件可能会让他想到
The tough conditions being imposed on Greece might remind HIM, ironically,
凡尔赛合约加诸德国的条件
of the deal imposed on Germany at Versailles.
当时欧洲的主流观点
The dominant thinking in Europe at the moment
我相信如今对希腊又犯了同样的错误
is exactly repeating the mistakes I believe, certainly for Greece,
如同一战结束时所犯的错误
as was made at the end of the First World War.
结论是  如果你因别人无法做到而迁怒于他  会以悲剧收场
There comes a point, if you visit on countries things they can never deliver, it will end in tears.
如果你观察当今欧洲正在发生什么
If you look at what's happening in the Eurozone today,
希腊大街上的暴动者
you have riots on the streets of Greece,
西班牙大罢工  葡萄牙大罢工
general strikes in Spain, general strikes in Portugal.
你会发现  这不正是因为我们吸取历史教训么?
You can see, well, aren't we just failing to learn the lessons of history here?
如果凯恩斯今天能和我一起在柏林
If Keynes could join me in Berlin today,
他肯定能体会欧元区危机的复杂性
he¹d surely appreciate the complexity of the crisis in the Eurozone
他能理解为什么普通德国民众觉得希腊应该付出代价
and he¹d understand why ordinary Germans feel it's time for Greece to pay its own way.
但是他也能理解  过分强迫希腊财政紧缩可能会自毁长城
But he also understood that imposing too much austerity could be self defeating.
我认为他会说 "让我们使希腊强大, 然后他们便能偿还欠债"
I think he would have said, "Let's make Greece strong, so then they can repay their debt."
只要债务人偿付  债权人就开心了
As long as a debtor pays, the creditor is happy.
可一旦债务人陷入困境
But as soon as a debtor gets into difficulties,
而他又是一个重要的债务人的话  债权人也会麻烦缠身
and if he's a very important debtor, the creditor has also problems.
因为他不能要回自己的钱
Because he won't get his money back.
面对今天影响着欧洲人们的危机
Faced with the crisis affecting the people of Europe today,
凯恩斯毫无疑问会给出一些解决办法
Keynes would undoubtedly have come up with some solutions.
事实上  凡尔赛合约签订的数年后
In fact, years after the Treaty of Versailles,
他公布了一个计划  是各国更好的合作
he'd unveil a plan for countries to work better together.
但首先  在一个更基本的问题
But first, there was a more basic question,
如何引导经济本身?
how to steer the economy itself?
掌控经济  使其更好的为我们服务
To tame the economy, to make it work for us,
凯恩斯意识到  首先要明白经济是如何运行的
Keynes realised you first had to understand how it worked.
上世纪20年代  理解经济的工具—经济学还很年轻
And the tool for doing that - economics - was still young in the 1920s,
但是却有着极大的野心
but it had grand ambitions.
人们希望可以预测经济走势
People hoped you'd be able to predict the movement of economies,
如同预测行星运动一样
like you could predict the movement of the planets.
凯恩斯也被这个观点所吸引  但他最终意识到经济不是行星
Keynes was drawn to that idea as well but he came to the conclusion economies weren't like planets.
经济更像人类
They were more like people.
无法准确预知它们接下来会走向何方
You never really knew what they were going to do next.
事实上他注意到  每当经济看上去可以准确预测的时候
In fact, he noticed, the times when economies looked most predictable,
通常也是事情即将错得离谱的时候
were usually the times when things were about to go disastrously wrong.
正如我们在2008年所感受的一样
It certainly felt like that in 2008,
在经历了史上最长的繁荣后  金融系统突然崩盘
when the world financial system imploded after one of the longest booms in history.
许多人现在声称这是可预见的
Many claim now to have seen it coming,
但在当时  更多人相信好日子会一直持续下去
but at the time, many more behaved as if the good times would go on and on.
不会有繁荣和衰退交替
No return to Tory boom and bust.
对未来经济发展太过确信
Being too sure about the economic future
是凯恩斯80年前警告过我们的又一个错误
was another mistake that Keynes had warned about 80 years ago.
因为他也犯过同样的错误
Because he'd made the same mistake himself.
一战结束后  他从财政部辞了职
After resigning from the Treasury after World War I,
凯恩斯回到了剑桥大学的国王学院
Keynes retreated to the sanctuary of his old college, Kings in Cambridge.
他是一个讲师  后来成为财务人员  主管学院的财务
He was a lecturer and later a bursar, looking after the college's finances.
他对概率论非常感兴趣
He had a special interest in probability theory,
它是数学的一个分支  试图根据过去以预测未来
a branch of mathematics that tries to predict the future from the evidence of the past.
当没有学习和写作的时候  凯恩斯经常在资本市场赌博
When he wasn¹t writing or studying, Keynes was often betting on the financial markets.
他需要钱  他认为投机是赚钱的好方法
He needed money and he thought speculation was a good way to get it.
同时也是检验他的信条的一个好方法
But it was also a great way for him to test his belief
即概率论和统计学
that probability theory and statistics
能有助于对市场运行进行预测
could help you predict the way markets were going to move.
他得到的成果好坏不一
He had very mixed results.
凯恩斯很年轻时就是一个投资者  他每天早上坐在床上
In his early years as an investor, Keynes sat in bed every morning
查看大量货币 股票 债券和商品的统计数据
poring over reams of statistics about currencies, shares, bonds and commodities.
当他确信找到了市场运行的方式时  他就参与交易
When he was sure he'd worked out which way the market would move, he'd make the deals.
剑桥学者大卫·钱伯斯花了大量的时间研究凯恩斯的投资策略
Cambridge academic David Chambers has spent a lot of time studying Keynes' investment strategies.
他有经济学知识  他对数字和统计有巨大的兴趣
Given this economic knowledge that he had, this great thirst that he had for numbers and statistics,
我认为  他相信自己能定义并描述经济周期
he believed I think that he could define, delineate, the business cycle.
其结果便是他能够选择
And as a consequence of that he would be able to pick
何时进入股票市场  买入股票
when was the right time to be in the stock market, to own shares,
何时离开股票市场转向债券市场
and when was the right time to come out of the stock market into bonds,
尤其是国债市场又或者套现
government bonds in particular, or, alternatively, cash.
但凯恩斯的精细计算都没能指出那迫在眉睫的灾难
But none of Keynes's elaborate calculations pointed out the disaster just around the corner.
1929年危机前夕  华尔街看上去还像是繁荣市场的牛尾
Wall Street before the crash in 1929 looked a lot like the tail end of our market boom.
投资者认为好日子没有尽头
Investors could see no end to the good times.
根据最新的数学模型  他们认为所有因素都已考虑在内
Armed with the very latest mathematical models, they thought they had everything covered.
突然  牛市泡沫破裂
Then the bubble burst.
世界市场崩盘  凯恩斯投资失败  和数百万的其他投资者一样
World markets collapsed and Keynes lost money, along with millions of others,
成为大萧条的铺路石
paving the way for the Great Depression.
他不再对预测未来有信心
His confidence in predicting the future was gone.
他一定为没有预测到大萧条而深感自责
He would have bitterly reproached himself for not foreseeing the Great Depression.
为什么他当时认为未来不是这样的
But he came to the view that the future is not like that,
如果有人预测正确
that anybody who happens to predict it right
那么更有可能是基于运气而不是基于判断
is likely to be doing so on the basis of luck rather than judgment.
凯恩斯的投机时代并没有结束
Keynes¹ speculating days weren¹t quite over.
数年后  他认为有可能要在国王学院的小礼堂存放数百吨小麦
Years later, he thought he might have to store hundreds of tons of wheat in King¹s College chapel,
因为他的一宗商品交易投资失败
after a commodity trade went wrong.
但是他改变了他的投资方法  他成为了一个富有的人
But he did change the way he invested, and became a wealthy man.
他从经济运行方式中得到了教训  而我们今天仍在与其做斗争
He¹d learned lessons about the way economies work that we still struggle with today.
人们无法摆脱经济的不确定性  因为经济是由人而不是数字构成
That you can never get rid of uncertainty and that economies are made up of people, not numbers.
凯恩斯比其他任何人更希望经济学能成为一门现代科学
More than anyone, Keynes wanted economics to be respected as a modern science.
但是他知道  经济学永远也不可能成为由一组确定的公式组成的科学
But he knew it was never going to be a science you could reduce to a set of equations,
可以有准确预测的科学
iron predictions,
因为经济学家总是要处理一些附加因素-人性
because economists were always going to have one extra thing to deal with, human nature.
如果你不知道未来
If you don't know about the future and you're trying to get a fix
你想弄清楚同一时间不同地点都在发生什么
on what's taking place anywhere in time,
你知道你必须听从群众
you know, you would defer to the crowds.
如果群众都走向特定方向 那么他们应该就是对的
If the crowd is moving in a certain direction, they must be right.
群众买什么  我就应该买什么
"The crowd's buying. What are they buying? I must buy, too."
群众卖什么  我就应该卖什么
"The crowd's selling, I must sell, too!"
这非常直觉  非常符合群体效应
And it's very animal. It¹s very herd.
从众心理帮助凯恩斯理解了
This idea of herd psychology helped Keynes make sense of the economic bubble
经济泡沫如何在1929年前夕不断的被吹大
that blew up in the years before the great crash of 1929.
它也能很好的解释2008年的金融危机
It can also do a pretty good job explaining our own great financial crash in 2008.
正常情况  任何经济学教材都会说
In normal times, any economic textbook now or in Keynes¹ time
价格上升  人们减少购买
would say if the price of something goes up, people buy less of it.
价格下降  人们增加购买
If the price goes down, they buy more.
这是市场运行的方式  但是凯恩斯认识到  当有泡沫时
That's how markets work. Except, Keynes realised, when you have bubbles.
人性的另一面将占接管理性
Then a different side of human nature takes over.
他会告诉我们 "房价在上升
It's the side that says,"Oh, house prices are going up.
股票在上升  我应该买更多  因为价格会继续上涨"
"Shares are going up. I shall buy more because the price is going to go up again."
当然  价格确实上升了  但是这成为了一个自我实现的螺旋
Which, of course, it does. It becomes a self-fulfilling spiral.
价格越来越高
Prices go up and up and up and up.
而最终  泡沫会破裂
Eventually, the bubble will burst. It always does.
2008年前夕
In the years before 2008,
我们是否忘记了凯恩斯告诉过我们的从众心理
did we forget what Keynes had taught us about herd psychology,
泡沫  以及经济的不确定性?
bubbles and the uncertainty of economic life?
银行家  投资者  政治家和我们
Did the bankers, investors, politicians and the rest of us
是不是只是盲目自信的认为好时光将继续?
simply get too confident in thinking the good times would go on forever?
我认为  因为人们开始真正静下来思考什么是风险
I think inasmuch as people actually sat down and thought about what were the risks,
什么是不确定性  才发现大部分人显然是愚蠢的
what are the uncertainties, then clearly a large number of people were manifestly found wanting.
当然  如果你不知道你在做什么
And, of course, if you don't know what you're doing,
毫无疑问  你会惨淡收场  而这正是确实发生的
it's not surprising that you end up being smashed to bits and that's precisely what happened.
凯恩斯的观点  国家不应该求助于其邻国
Keynes¹s big ideas, that countries shouldn¹t beggar their neighbours,
市场不可预测  都是出自于他的自身经历
that markets were unpredictable, all came out of his own experience.
大萧条还导致形成了了他最重要的观点
Now the Great Depression produced his most important idea yet,
增加了他掌控经济的需求的紧迫性
and added real urgency to his need to tame the economy.
他意识到  经济可能会衰退
What he realised was, economies might sink
且不会自动回归正常
and then not automatically float back up.
在今天的西方经济形势下  这听起来很熟悉
Looking around the western economies today, that does sound a bit familiar.
30年代早期  外面的世界都非常悲观
In the early '30s, the outside world was deep in gloom,
领取失业救济金的排队越来越长  到处都有工厂破产倒闭
with dole queues lengthening and factories closing everywhere,
但是凯恩斯的生活是幸福的
but Keynes¹ life was blissful.
这时他已经成名  他那些前卫的布鲁姆斯伯里帮的朋友甚至都被他震惊了
By now he was famous, and he'd shocked even his avant-garde Bloomsbury friends
因为他和一个俄罗斯芭蕾舞演员结婚了
by marrying a Russian ballerina.
而在此之前  他一直是同性恋
Up till then, he¹d been gay.
艺术 写书 恋爱  这就是凯恩斯的全部生活
Art, books, love affairs, for Keynes this was what life was all about.
但是他知道  可能比他的布鲁姆斯伯里帮朋友们更知道是继承的财产
But he understood, probably more keenly than his Bloomsbury friends with their inherited wealth,
帮助他保持了正常的生活
that money kept the whole thing afloat.
如果没有正常运行的经济  就不可能有文明的社会
You couldn¹t have a civilised society without a well-functioning economy.
周一早上  当他回到现实生活的时候
When he was back in the real world on Monday morning,
他发现英国经济完全失控了
he could see the British economy wasn¹t working at all.
英国经济已经衰退了很长一段时间
Britain had been in a slump for years.
传统经济学家认为  如果工人降低工资
Classical economists said that if workers would just agree to wage cuts,
商人就会继续投资  创造工作机会  经济就会重新繁荣
businessmen would invest again, create jobs, and the economy would revive.
但是凯恩斯不这么认为  他认为复苏受到了悲观情绪的制约
But Keynes disagreed. He thought the way to recovery was being blocked by pessimism,
或者说是受意志消沉的制约
or low animal spirits.
凯恩斯洞悉这一切的深层原因是
The big insight of Keynes behind all of this
市场经济缺乏自我稳定机制
was that a market economy is not self-stabilising.
当你情感上经历巨大变化
When you get very big changes in animal spirits, in sentiment,
人们生产未来出售的产品
the people who are producing to sell in the future
突然开始担心有可能未来没有需求了  他们就开始停止生产
suddenly worry that actually maybe there won't be the demand in the future, so they stop producing.
想要跳出低产出的循环是很困难的
To get out of that low output trap can be very difficult.
凯恩斯认为经济持续衰退
Keynes realisation that an economy could stay sunk indefinitely
毫无疑问是对传统思维的巨大突破
was a radical break with conventional thinking.
传统经济学认为  只要时间足够长  经济会好起来的
The classical approach said the economy would get better, we just had to give it time.
但是在凯恩斯看来  明显没有任何好转
But looking around, it seemed obvious to Keynes that it wasn¹t getting any better
而且为什么不好起来的原因也再明显不过了
and it seemed blindingly obvious why it wasn¹t.
每次有人失业  加入失业救济领取队伍  他们获得的可支配收入越少
Every time someone lost their jobs and joined the dole queue, they had less money to spend,
意味着他们买更少的商品
so that would mean fewer goods were bought.
意味着可能更多的人会失业
It would probably mean more job losses.
会进入一个螺旋形下降的趋势  看不到明显的出路
You could get caught in a downward spiral with no obvious way out.
今天我们认为这是很显而易见的
Now it seems equally obvious to us today,
但是当时  这些都是全新的
but back then it was all very new.
凯恩斯认为  商业世界的悲观情绪会传染给每个人
Keynes thought the low animal spirits in the business world were now infecting everyone.
1931年  他通过无线广播中号召大家行动
In a radio broadcast in 1931, he made a dramatic call for action.
交易和就业的下降
The slump in trade and employment
是有史以来最严重的
are as bad as the worst which have ever occurred.
个人和国家的行动  才是治病的良方
Activity and enterprise, both individually and nationally, must be the cure.
如今  凯恩斯的追随者也在做同样的呼吁
Today, Keynes¹ followers have made similar calls.
大衰退开始后几年
Years after the start of the recession,
经济为了回到之前的水平苦苦挣扎
the economy is still struggling to get back to where it was.
即使不是凯恩斯  也能发现人们情绪悲观
You don¹t have to be Keynes to see animal spirits are low.
而他观点是否能帮助人们恢复信心又是另一个问题了
Whether his ideas can revive them is another question.
凯恩斯关于国家陷入困境的思考
Keynes¹ insight that countries could just get stuck
可能是他对经济思想的最重要贡献
was probably his most important contribution to economic thinking.
但是  他不仅仅只是理解经济  他希望能使其更好的运行
But he didn¹t just want to understand economies, he wanted to make them work better.
对于如何从衰退中复苏  他有很多建议
He had plenty of advice for getting out of a slump,
其中最有争议性的应该是  政府可以花他们还没有的钱
but the most controversial was that governments should spend money they haven¹t got.
在我看来  当今政治最大的争议在于
To my mind, the biggest argument in politics today
危机以来  国家是干涉过多还是干预不足
is over whether countries have done too much of that since the crisis hit or not enough.
凯恩斯70年前已经死了
Keynes might have died almost seven decades ago,
但在这亚利桑那沙漠中  他关于帮助经济运行的观点仍然活着
but out here in the Arizona desert, his big idea for getting the economy moving again lives on.
在希拉本德  他们正在建造世界上最大的太阳能工厂
At Gila Bend, they're building the biggest solar power plant of its kind in the world.
面积达到3.5平方英里
The site covers over three-and-a-half square miles.
100万个镜子将获取足够的能量
Nearly a million mirrors will capture enough energy
为7万美国家庭提供清洁能源
to provide 70,000 American homes with clean power.
对于这个遥远地方的人们来说  对凯恩斯来说
But for the people in this remote region, and for John Maynard Keynes,
这个工厂最重要的意义在于提供就业
probably the most important thing this plant will produce is employment.
我妻子和我之中
Between my wife and I,
我们有两年时间处于失业状态
we probably spent two years out of work.
谢天谢地  不是同时
Thank God, not at the same time but...
但是我们  受到了一些很严重的打击
But we, er, we took some very significant hits.
公司的人力资源部门告诉我们  他们一天要收到300份简历
The company that sources our manpower tells me they receive 300 resumes per day.
很多人都在找工作
There's a lot of people looking for work.
在此地找到工作的人们觉得非常幸运
And the people who have jobs out here are very... feel very lucky to have their jobs.
事实上  这个工厂是一项巨大的凯恩斯主义实验的一部分
In effect, this plant is part of a vast Keynesian experiment.
经济危机后
In the wake of the crash,
美国政府花费了7500亿美金资助类似项目
the US government stumped up three-quarters of a trillion dollars for projects like this one
用于创造更多的就业和促进经济增长
to create jobs and growth.
常规情况下  人们想经营这个工厂
In normal times, say the people who run this site,
必须先从商业银行取得15亿贷款
they would have raised the billion and a half dollars to get things going from commercial banks.
但是现在不是常规时期
But these aren't normal times.
由于经济危机  我们必须...
Because of that downturn, we had to, er...
寻找融资的其他渠道
..look for alternative sources of financing.
当然  在这种情况下
And, of course, in this context
联邦担保贷款计划帮了我们很大的忙
the Federal loan guarantee programme here in the US has helped a lot.
事实上  如果没有公共计划  这个工厂可能不会存在
In fact without that kind of public programmes this plant would have never been a reality.
如今  我们习惯了政府支出
Now we¹re used to governments using their cash
在私人投资萎缩的情况下  帮助我们摆脱困境
to try to bring the economy to life in hostile environments where private money's drying up.
但是在凯恩斯年代  这是极具争议的观点
But back in Keynes¹ day, it was a much more controversial idea.
1930年代  凯恩斯在伦敦布鲁姆斯伯里街的这个房子里度过了数周
In the 1930s, Keynes spent weekdays at his home here in London¹s Bloomsbury district.
他写了很多文章和小册子
He wrote countless articles and pamphlets
解释一些措施如何能帮助解决大衰退问题  为什么这些措施应该被执行
explaining how something could and should be done to tackle this Great Depression.
常规时期  凯恩斯认为货币政策是有效的方法
In normal times, Keynes thought monetary policy was the best way to help the economy.
降低利率  鼓励借款和消费
You cut interest rates to encourage people to borrow and spend more
和投资
and companies to invest.
但悲观情绪严重时  这些措施就不够充分了
But when animal spirits are really low that might not be enough.
公司看不到新增投资的意义
Companies might not see the point of making new investments,
利率再低  人们也没有借款的需求
people might not want to borrow no matter how cheap it was.
凯恩斯认为政府应该用财政支出去解决供需矛盾
That¹s when Keynes thought government did need to make up the gap with more public spending.
凯恩斯建议  政府应该雇佣员工拆除伦敦南部然后重建
Keynes suggested the government should hire people to demolish South London and then rebuild it.
他是开玩笑的  但是他指出了一个严肃的问题
He wasn¹t serious, but he was making a serious point.
如果政府借款创造了工作机会  人们将消费更多
If the government borrowed to create jobs, people would spend more,
信心提升  经济复苏
confidence would rise, and the economy would recover.
如果选择的时机正确  他认为额外支出将会创造相同的收入 If you picked the right moment, he insisted the extra spending would pay for itself
通过产生更高的税收收入
by producing higher tax revenues.
在尝试劝说财政部的过程中  他遇到了很多困难
He did have enormous trouble trying to persuade the Treasury,
所谓的财政部观点认为
the so-called "Treasury view",
人们应该在商业周期的低谷借款
that you should borrow at the bottom of a business cycle.
以经济观点来看  需要的就是增加经济中的需求量
But in economic terms what you need is more demand in the economy
而且你可以按凯恩斯所建议的方法来做
and you can do that in the ways Keynes suggested.
对付经济衰退的简单凯恩斯主义药方
Naive Keynesian prescriptionsof simply responding to recession
是提高财政赤字  不考虑其后果
by raising the budget deficit,as if this had no effect,
不考虑对其他经济变量的不利影响
no adverse effect,on other economic variables,
我认为这是一个非常危险的政策
I really think are verydangerous policy prescriptions.
30年代  凯恩斯发现  很多英国政治家也有同样的观点
In the '30s, Keynes found that most British politicians had a similar view...
高负债是危险的
high borrowing was dangerous.
他认为他能在美国找到接受能力更强的受众
He thought he might have a more receptive audience in America.
毕竟  在大西洋两岸他都是名人
After all, he was now a celebrity on both sides of the Atlantic,
美国的经济形势还更加绝望
and the economic situation in America was desperate.
GDP下降至70%
Gross national product was down to almost 70%.
全国失业率达到25%
You had unemployment nationally at 25%.
在芝加哥和底特律  失业率甚至达到了50%
In places like Chicago and Detroit, unemployment was up to 50%.
半数人口失业
Over half the population unemployed.
胡佛总统解决大衰退的办法是削减支出  提高税负
President Hoover¹s solution to the Great Depression had been spending cuts and tax rises.
他提出了一个观点  我最近也听到其他人提起
He'd made an argument we¹ve heard others make more recently.
国家的财政平衡有助于提升信心和鼓励就业
Balancing the country¹s books would create confidence and encourage investment.
没有发生  从未发生
Didn't happen. Never has happened.
当你削减政府支出
When you cut back government spending
特别在一个大衰退的环境下  需求锐减
in a situation such as a recession or depression, demand goes down,
失业率上升  这是一个恶性循环
unemployment goes up, and it's a vicious circle.
当失业率不断攀升  经济下降的时候  信心很难恢复
Confidence isn't restored when unemployment goes up and when business goes down.
信心都被侵蚀了
Confidence is eroded.
胡佛的继任者  罗斯福总统采用了另一种方法
Hoover¹s successor, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, had a different approach.
同样的观点今天也在被重复提及
Again, echoing arguments made today,
他认为政府应该加大支出  走出困境
he thought the government should spend its way out of trouble.
这个国家要求我们有所行动
This nation is asking for action
立刻行动!
and action now!
1934年  凯恩斯到达美国
When Keynes arrived in America, in 1934,
没有任何证据表明他劝说美国政府采用凯恩斯主义
there¹s no evidence that he persuaded the US government to adopt Keynesianism.
无论如何  他们已经在用
They were doing it anyway.
凯恩斯和罗斯福总统只有一次会面
Keynes had his one and only meeting with President Roosevelt.
从各方面来讲  会面都进展得不顺利
By all accounts, it didn¹t go very well.
凯恩斯认为罗斯福总统不是经济学家
Keynes thought the President was no economist.
总统认为凯恩斯有点聪明过头
The President thought Keynes was a bit too clever for his own good.
但是他们在重要事情上达成了一致
But they did agree on the most important thing.
是政府采取行动的时候了
This was no time for government to sit on its hands.
是一个历史性实验的时候了
It was time for an historic experiment.
罗斯福新政  一个巨大的政府投资计划
The New Deal, a vast programme of government-funded projects
让失业大军参与工作
to put armies of jobless to work.
从那以后  它成为凯恩斯主义
Ever since, it¹s been the celebrated example
刺激萎靡经济的政策的经典案例
of a Keynesian effort to boost flagging economies.
那个时代最有象征意义的工程是
And there¹s no more iconic project of that era than this one.
胡佛大坝
Hoover Dam.
横跨科罗拉多河  连接内华达和亚利桑那
Built across the Colorado River, bordering Nevada and Arizona,
他曾是世界上最大的建设工程
it was the biggest construction project in the world.
我绝对可以称之为凯恩斯工程
I would call it a Keynesian project, absolutely.
政府投资大量美元和财政赤字
The government stepped in with money.
成果就是这座胡佛大坝
Built a deficit, and out of that came Hoover Dam,
它给予了成千上万人新的生活
which gave thousands, tens of thousands of people,
给他们工资可以用于消费
a new life, money to spend.
来自美国各地大量的工人
Armies of workers from across America
花了5年时间  从延绵山岭岩石中开凿隧道
tunnelled for five years through mile upon mile of mountain rock
建成一个巨大的发电站并投入使用
to build, what was in effect, a vast power generator,
为美国大片的居民提供电力
providing electricity for huge swathes of the country.
它充实了经济
It primed the economy.
1.65亿的投资
165 million investment,
带动了数十亿的经济增长
which produced billions in growth, economic growth.
仅仅8英里处有一个博尔德城  是大坝修建工人的住所
Just eight miles away is Boulder City, built to house the workers building the dam.
这条街边的所有房子  我们现在称为"蝙蝠居"
All these houses along these avenues are what we now call "ding-bat houses".
他们是为工人修建的住所
They were the homes built for the workers.
他们在大坝修建过程中建成  建设速度很快
They were put up to last through the construction of the dam. Very quickly built.
由于人们出乎意料的在这里住了下来
But because people stayed, which they didn't anticipate,
而且家人也和他们一起生活
families still lived in them.
罗杰经营着小镇的旅店
Roger Shoaff runs the town's hotel.
他认为博尔德城展示了在大萧条中
He thinks Boulder City shows how in a depression
政府支出是如何推动了私人消费和投资的
extra government spending CAN trigger private spending and investment, too,
从而增加经济效益
adding to the economic benefits.
这就是凯恩斯所称的乘数效应
It's what Keynes called "the multiplier".
第二年年末  他们住进了一个小镇  一个功能齐全的小镇
By the end of the second year, they lived in a town, a full town,
有零售商店和餐厅
fully operating town with retail stores and restaurants
有医疗设施和娱乐设施  这一切在不到两年的时间内都发生了
and medical facilities and recreational facilities. It happened in less than two years.
凯恩斯主义的批评者经常说  收益是短期的  而成本是长期的
Critics of Keynesian spending plans often say the benefits are fleeting and the costs permanent.
但是博尔德城已经扎根并繁荣
But Boulder City took root and thrived.
对于那些生活在此的人来说  如果没有罗斯福新政
Those who still live here say if it hadn¹t been for the New Deal,
这里仍然是一片荒漠
this would still be desert.
胡佛大坝也许帮助了当地经济
Hoover Dam might have helped the local area,
但罗斯福新政终结了大萧条实际上则是一则神话
but it¹s actually a myth that the New Deal ended the Great Depression.
一场世界大战耗费了政府所有的额外支出
It took a world war and all the extra government spending that went with that, finally,
最终也将经济带出低迷
to bring the economy out of the doldrums.
你也许怀疑  世界大战是否真的是检验凯恩斯论据的最好方法
You might wonder whether a world war was really the best test of Keynes¹ arguments.
但是从那以后  所谓的凯恩斯主义政治
But ever since then, so-called "Keynesian policies"
就指政府面临危机的时候该做什么
have been what governments do when faced with emergencies.
2008年金融危机是最近很长一段时间里面最大的危机
And the crisis of 2008 was the biggest emergency anyone had seen for a long time.
当全球金融系统崩溃
When the global financial system crashed,
世界面临又一场大萧条的可能
the world faced the real possibility of another Great Depression.
多年来  政府一直指望自由市场
Governments had been preaching the free market for years.
但当面临经济灾难时  他们转投过气的凯恩斯主义
But faced with this economic disaster they reached again for the old Keynesian levers.
这是一个经典的凯恩斯主义的回答
It was a classic Keynesian response.
当个人和企业都停止支出时
When individuals and businesses stop spending money,
如果政府也同时停止支出
if the government also stops spending money at the same time,
会发生什么?  基本上经济会崩溃
then what happens? The economy, basically, crashes.
目标旨在提振信心或提升乐观情绪
The aim was to boost confidence, or animal spirits,
为使得人们更易于借款  投资和消费
by making it easier to borrow, invest and spend.
利率降至有记录以来的最低值  0.5%
Interest rates were slashed to just half of one percent, the lowest on record.
我们现在都在一个未知的领域
We¹re all now in uncharted territory.
当利率下降至最低值时
Then, when interest rates couldn¹t go much lower,
英格兰银行为经济直接注入了数百亿英镑
the Bank of England started pumping billions of pounds directly into the economy.
接下来几个月  账面上有750亿英镑
It¹s literally creating £75 billion in the next few months
还会流向市场
to get money moving around the economy again.
甚至增值税也被暂停征收了
Even VAT was temporarily cut.
通过鼓励投资  商品和服务的价格将下降  进而刺激经济增长
It'll make goods and services cheaper and by encouraging spending it will help stimulate growth.
2009年  尽管全球经济仍在挣扎
In 2009, with the global economy still tottering,
各国首脑聚集伦敦  为全球经济体签署一项凯恩斯主义的援助计划
leaders gathered in London to endorse a Keynesian rescue plan for the entire world.
这是各国共同协作的时代
This is the day that the world came together
共同击退全球经济危机
to fight back against the global recession.
我认为解释全球贸易萎缩很困难
I find it very hard to explain the collapse in world trade,
从08年末至09年春天  全球贸易下降15%
of over 15% between the end of '08 and the beginning of spring '09,
除了用野兽精神  或者信心  很难找到其他合适的词汇了
in terms of anything other than an extraordinary collapse of "animal spirits", or confidence.
2009年有些情况出现转机  但远不是全部
Now some of that was turned around in 2009, but by no means all.
就连2009年的大援助计划和其表象也相去甚远
Even that great rescue plan of 2009 wasn¹t quite what it seemed.
首相布朗的所有谈话中说明  英国自身的刺激政策实际上非常小
For all Gordon Brown¹s talk, Britain's own stimulus plan was actually one of the smallest,
因为我们的政府已经比其他发达国家有更高的负债
because our government was already borrowing more than any other advanced economy.
因此  尽管是一个像布朗一样的凯恩斯主义首相 也不会认为我们能借更多的钱
So even a Keynesian Prime Minister like Gordon Brown didn¹t think we could borrow a lot more.
他的继任者认为我们应该借更少
His successor thinks we should borrow much less.
我们现任首相在基本的观点上都不认同凯恩斯主义
We now have a Prime Minister who, on one fundamental point, appears to disagree with Keynes.
政府在处理常规衰退时的一些措施
Some of the normal things that governments can do to deal with a normal recession,
例如借款  减税  增加政府支出
like borrowing to cut taxes or increasing spending.
这些都不再有效  因为他们使得负债增长
These things won't work because they lead to more debt,
从而可能导致危机加剧
which would make the crisis worse.
解决债务危机的唯一办法是偿还债务
The only way out of a debt crisis is to deal with your debts.
我怀疑  凯恩斯可能不会用当今首相同样的措施
I suspect that Keynes probably wouldn't have used exactly the Prime Minister's formulation.
我认为  在某些程度上
I think that Keynes would have accepted at some point
我们要掉头转向更平衡的预算
that you have to head back towards a more balanced budget,
特别是  不想把债务都留给后代的时候
particularly if you don't want to stack debts on future generations.
我觉得应该注意的是  像英国这样的国家
To me the remarkable thing is that countries like the UK,
有选择
that have a choice,
自愿实施财政紧缩政策
are voluntarily putting themselves through austerity
而且  我们几乎确定的知道会发生什么
and, almost certainly, we will know, we know what will happen.
经济会越来越弱
The economy will get weaker.
失业率会上升
Erm, unemployment will go up,
会有大量的
and there will be an enormous amount
不必要的痛苦
of unnecessary suffering.
这个争议在大西洋两岸将不断持续
This argument will run and run on both sides of the Atlantic.
在亚利桑那  巨额支出用于修建太阳能工厂
In Arizona, the massive spending programme that built this solar power plant
提供大量新的就业机会并不是拯救美国经济的良方
and let thousands clock on for new jobs hasn't been a miracle cure for the US economy.
也许解药没有起作用是因为剂量太小
Maybe the medicine didn¹t work because the dose was too small.
也许  绝大多数西方国家背负的堆积如山的债务
Or maybe, the mountain of debt weighing on most western economies
意味着凯恩斯主义的常规方法已经失效
means the Keynesian route to recovery is simply shut off.
我们今天处在了债务最高的时期
We are in a stratosphere today
是我们以前从未经历  也许这还好
that we just have not seen before and maybe it's fine,
但是没有其他国家有过如此高的负债水平
but no other countries, rarely, have seen these debt levels.
公共措施 私人投资 其他措施都有风险
Public, private and other measures, they're risks.
直到1940年  凯恩斯已经声名显赫
By the 1940s, Keynes was riding high.
在剑桥  关于他的戏剧不断上演
His theatre, here in Cambridge, was thriving.
他回到了财政部  为二战进行融资
He was back in the Treasury helping finance the Second World War,
他的作品被认为是杰作
and his books were being hailed as masterpieces.
但是他还在探寻最后一个重要思想
But he had one last big idea to pursue,
对当时和现代世界都有着深远影响
with profound implications for the world, then and now.
凯恩斯关于处置毁损经济体的观点已经被证实了
Keynes¹s ideas for fixing broken economies had now been tested.
但是二战结束
But towards the end of World War II,
他获得了一个在全球经济上印上他的标识的机会
he got a chance to leave his mark on the entire global economy.
在一个高度一体化的世界  他比以前更确信
In a more integrated world he was more convinced than ever
各国都需要一个机构来促成其合作
that countries needed institutions to force them together, make them co-operate.
使得一战后的灾难不再重现
The catastrophe after World War I could never happen again.
凯恩斯访问美国中最重要一次发生在1944年
The single most important trip to America that Keynes ever took was in 1944
在新罕布什尔州的布雷顿森林的一个私人度假村
to the exclusive resort of Bretton Woods in New Hampshire.
他加入了来自超过40个不同国家的代表团
He was joining delegates from over 40 different countries,
负责建立战后全球经济基础
all charged with laying the foundations of a new post-war global economy.
他们希望重构这个系统
They wanted to rebuild the system.
不仅仅因为战争  还因为大萧条
Not just from the war, but from the Great Depression.
金融系统已经被摧毁
The financial system had just been destroyed.
凯恩斯相信  20-30年代的经济混乱主要是由于战争导致的
The economic chaos of the '20s and '30s was largely responsible for the war, Keynes believed.
各国都更关注规划自己的道路
Countries had all focused on charting their own path,
而很少关心周围发生了什么
without very much thought for what was going around them.
整个世界都已经为失败的合作付出了巨大的代价
The world had paid a terrible price for that failure to co-operate.
伦敦和华盛顿的官员们都下定决心
There was a determination among officials in London and Washington
不能让悲剧再度发生
that we couldn't do this again.
我们必须稳定世界经济
We had to fix the world's economy.
我们不能回到战前的经济危机
That we had to... We couldn't go back to the kind of economic crisis
因为我们无法再次承受战争
we'd had before because we couldn't afford another world war.
世界各地的代表齐聚华盛顿山度假酒店
As representatives from across the world gathered here at Mount Washington Hotel,
其他地方仍在激烈交战
elsewhere there was still ferocious fighting.
但是一旦战争结束  凯恩斯知道  为了世界经济繁荣
But once the war was over, Keynes knew, for the world economy to prosper,
各国需要比以前更紧密的合作
countries would need to work together much more closely.
只有两个代表团在会议上有绝对影响力
Only two delegations at the conference really counted
凯恩斯的英国代表团和美国代表团
Keynes¹ British team and the Americans.
两者都认为应该有控制措施
Both agreed that there should be controls
防止汇率剧烈波动
to prevent currencies fluctuating too wildly against each other.
他们同意应该有一个机构  后来成为世界银行和国际货币基金组织
They agreed that institutions, that later became the World Bank and International Monetary Fund,
扶植第三世界国家的贸易和发展
should be there to foster trade and growth in poorer economies.
这其中最大的收获是我们的认知
Well, the big gain from it was the recognition
国家之间应该相互协作解决他们的宏观经济问题
that countries need to work together to resolve their macro-economic problems.
按独立解决问题的方式处理是不够的
It's just not enough to pretend that you can do it as an island.
地理上你也许是孤岛  但是经济上不是
You may be an island geographically but you're not economically.
但是在关键问题上  凯恩斯失败了
But on one crucial issue, Keynes failed.
美国人坚持  像他们这样的出口大国
The Americans were adamant that rich exporting countries, like them,
不应该扩大内需  减少出口来平衡世界贸易
shouldn¹t have to spend more and export less to balance world trade.
大额贸易赤字的弱国必须加快发展
It was weak countries with big trade deficits that had to shape up.
如果布雷顿森林的每个人都接受凯恩斯的逻辑
If everyone at Bretton Woods had accepted Keynes' logic,
所有参与方合作才能保持全球经济平衡
that it takes ALL sides to keep the global economy in balance,
今天的世界也许会更好
the world today might be in a lot better shape.
这个古老的东德电视塔是德国统一的标志
This old East German television tower is a symbol of reunified Germany.
这些天  对欧盟的感情越来越淡
But these days feelings of European unity are in short supply.
各国部长在柏林  为在欧元区国家强制实施紧缩政策作斗争
Ministers here in Berlin want struggling Eurozone countries to impose tough measures
使其经济恢复正常
to get their economies into shape.
大国乐于提供帮助
The stronger countries have been willing to help
如提供大额贷款  我不认为凯恩斯会觉得这样就行了
by offering massive loans, but I don¹t think Keynes would have thought that was enough.
凯恩斯认为  全球经济的运行  必须是双向的
Keynes thought, for the global economy to work, it had to be a two-way street.
所以  那些已经向其他国家大力举债的小国
So the weak countries, that had run up a lot of debt with the rest of the world,
他们也必须更具有竞争力  学习偿还贷款
they did have to become more competitive, learn to pay their way.
但是出口大国  他们也必须有所作为
But the rich exporters... Well, they had to do their bit as well...
增加进口  减少出口
spending more on other countries' goods and exporting less,
稍微不那么有竞争力
becoming a bit less competitive.
现在  凯恩斯的这部分建议在德国并没有有效实施
Now that¹s a bit of Keynesian advice that doesn¹t go down well here in Germany at all.
如果你说  德国应该减少出口  降低竞争力
If you say Germany should export less or become less competitive,
民众意见将是"你疯了"
the popular view is, "That's mad!"
为什么其他人已经很弱的情况下  我们还要变弱？
Why getting us weak when others are already weak?
毫无疑问  这是一个错误的结论。
And, certainly, that's the wrong conclusion.
已经有征兆表明  德国正在向这个方向努力
There are signs of movement on Germany¹s side of the street.
国内汽车销售上升
Domestic car sales have been going up.
但是出口仍然是德国经济政策的核心支柱
But exports are still a central plank of the country¹s economic policies.
汽车出口在过去两年上升1/3
And car exports are up by almost a third in the past two years.
德国消费者最近已经开增加消费
German consumers have been spending more lately.
但是仍不足以为困境中的国家如希腊提供足够的机会
But not enough to provide much of a selling opportunity for struggling countries like Greece.
一个很流行的方法是告诉德国普通家庭"请多消费
That's a very popular approach, to tell German private households, "Please, spend more.
不要对钱这么吝啬"
"Don't be so greedy with your money."
但是我认为这是错的
Er, but I think that's, that's wrong.
因为人们看着他的收入  然后说"我无法承受"  这是事实
Because people look at their income and say, "I can't afford it, simply." And that's true.
我的意思是  过去几年工资上升幅度很小
I mean we have had very weak wage increases during the past years.
这才是问题的关键  你必须有更高的工资
And that's the point where you have to have higher wages.
才能支出这些工资
And these higher wages you could certainly spend.
当德国的消费比过去增大时  才能对我们有所帮助
And then German consumption would be much stronger than it was in the past and that will help us.
高通胀的记忆仍然在刺痛德国人
Memories of hyperinflation are still raw in Germany.
很少人愿意为了他们羸弱的欧洲邻居  放弃他们辛苦赢得的经济稳定
Few want to put their hard-won economic stability at risk for their weaker European neighbours.
在国际范围内  国家之间的差距更加明显
The divisions between countries at a global level are even clearer.
对于凯恩斯期待的真正的全球经济合作  强国和弱国为了共同利益进行合作
Leaders pay lip service to Keynes¹ dream of a truly co-ordinated global economy,
各国领袖都还在做表面文章
where the strong work with the weak for the benefit of all.
但是有一些小的证据表明他们开始做一些实事
But there¹s little sign of them actually doing it.
我认为凯恩斯看到我们的世界
I think that Keynes would look at our world
欧元区问题  银行危机
the troubles in the Eurozone, the banking crisis
会说  这是一个非常令人害怕的地方
and say it was a pretty scary place,
没有布雷顿森林体系里他主张的检查和平衡
without many of the checks and balances that he argued for at Bretton Woods.
但是他也会说  他确实说了
But he'd also say - he DID say...
真正的全球经济是令人振奋的
that a really global economy was tremendously exciting,
有巨大的潜能帮助我们提高生活水平
with huge potential to improve all of our lives.
如果政府能够找到实施方法
If governments could only work out how to put into practise
将他一直坚持的基本理念付诸实施
that basic insight that he kept coming back to.
我们就真的团结在一起了
We really are all in it together.
更好的国际机构当然是好事
Sure, it would be great to have better multinational institutions
凯恩斯是这方面的先驱
and Keynes was a pioneer in that.
他信奉  为了维护国际金融秩序  这类机构是非常有用的
He was a big believer. In order to fix the international financial system that would be very helpful.
如果有人具备了凯恩的的吸引力和影响力
And maybe somebody with the sort of magnetism and gravitas
他能够在某种程度上促进事件的发展
and stature of Keynes could somehow catalyse that.
但是凯恩斯却是非常罕见的人物
But he is a rare person indeed.
他留下了一笔非凡的遗产
Keynes left an extraordinary legacy.
他不仅改变了经济学
He didn¹t just transform economics,
也改变了全球无数人的生活
he changed the lives of billions of people around the globe.
其中包括很多1880年代出生的人
There aren¹t many people born in the 1880s
你经常会在当前的辩论中听到他们的名字
whose name you hear as often as Keynes in current debates.
他关于国家不应向邻国乞讨的观点
His ideas that countries shouldn¹t beggar their neighbours,
关于经济是不可预测、可能陷入困境的观点
that economies were deeply unpredictable,
都改变了我们思考世界的方式
could get stuck in slumps, have changed the way we think about the world.
但是凯恩斯目前能为我们做什么?
But what can Keynes actually do for us right now?
回到坎布里亚郡  很显然  凯恩斯帮助了他们
Back in Cumbria, it¹s clear what Keynes has done for them.
政府干预帮助他们保持了倍耐力工厂的运营
Government intervention will help keep Pirelli¹s tyre factory open,
提供了大量的就业机会
and provide a lot of employment.
在主流政治圈中并没有很多人质疑凯恩斯下述基本原理
In the political mainstream, there aren¹t many who challenge Keynes¹ basic message
不能放任经济自由发展
that you can¹t leave economies to drive themselves.
凯恩斯是20世纪一个非常有影响力的人物
Keynes was a very dominant force in the 20th century
我猜他在21世纪还会保持这种影响力
and my guess is he will remain a dominant force in the 21st century,
因此我认为他将成为有史以来最伟大的经济学家之一
which is why I think he will go down as one of the greatest economists the world has produced.
80年前  建造这个大坝  缓和了大萧条
80 years ago, building this dam eased the Great Depression.
当今政府举债的成本比以往都要低
With the government borrowing more cheaply than ever before,
你也许会认为  罗斯福新政类似的投资在今天也可以起到显著作用
you might think the case for New Deal-type investments was equally strong today.
但是考虑到已有的国家债务  没有人可以肯定继续举债
But given the sheer volume of public debt, no-one can promise that piling on more borrowing
将成为神奇的疗方
will be a miracle cure.
典型的凯恩斯主义方案被认为是
What is thought of as a typical Keynesian solution
举债  举债...消费  消费...还有减税
to get more debt, borrow money, spend, spend, spend and cut taxes.
今天使用这些需要更审慎
That needs to be used more judiciously here,
因为  最终仍需要偿还债务
because, at the end of the day, you¹ve got to get rid of this debt.
这是一个持久的过程
This is a very long haul.
我认为  没有人可以避开这个过程来提升经济
I don't think anything just boosts your way and zooms your way out of this.
没有神奇的解决方案
There just is no magic bullet.
那么凯恩斯最后的重要观点  各国应该紧密合作对当今世界有何影响?
And what of Keynes¹ final big idea, that countries are all in it together?
自从布雷顿森林体系建立  各国逐渐接受我们必须合作才能繁荣的观点
Since Bretton Woods, the world has grudgingly accepted that we have to co-operate to prosper.
但是我们仍在摸索如何将其付诸行动
But we¹re struggling to make it work in practise.
他会很担心  非常担心
He'd be worried. He'd be very worried.
他将对世界各国发展不平衡非常关注
He'd have been very concerned about the growth of inequality worldwide.
他将对是否有国家开始向邻国乞讨非常关注
Er, he'd be very concerned that there was a return to beggar my neighbour policies.
我毫不怀疑  他会警告我们会有地方性战争
I have no doubt that he would be warning of regional war
及其带来的全部危害
and all its dangers.
他将很害怕
He'd be very frightened
导致一战和二战的经济环境
that the circumstances that led to war in 14/18 and 39/45
正在逐步出现在我们面前
were, on a slow-burn basis, unfolding in front of us again.
也许凯恩斯现在能为我们做的
Maybe the biggest thing Keynes could do for us now
就是让我们注意那些引导他一生的品质
would be to remind us of the traits that guided him all of his life...
想象力和乐观主义
imagination and optimism.
他如果能来到现代  一定会很乐于研究这些复杂的问题
He came along and was willing to examine these profound problems
以一种前所未有的方式
in ways that no-one had done before.
他最大的遗产是对人性坚定的信念
His great legacy is that fundamental belief in humanity,
对政府和社会能力坚定的信念
that fundamental belief in the ability of government and society
政府能全心全意为那些贫困和需要帮助的人服务
to dedicate itself to helping those that are less fortunate and need our help.
1946年  凯恩斯在其深爱的苏克塞斯当斯遭受了致命的心脏疾病
In 1946, Keynes suffered a fatal heart attack in his beloved Sussex Downs.
享年62岁  他留下了改变世界的遗产
Just 62, he left a legacy that changed the world.
但是他也留下了一个谜
But he also left an enigma.
他认为他能掌控经济让其为我们服务
He thought we should try to tame the power of money to make it work for us,
但是他也告诉我  经济本质上是不可预测的
but he also taught us that economies were fundamentally unpredictable.
这是一对我们今天仍在处理的矛盾
It¹s a contradiction we¹re still grappling with today.
为政府积极作为铺平道路  凯恩斯做得比其他任何人更多
More than anyone, Keynes paved the way for activist government.
他说  你能够也应该让世界经济更好运行
He said you could and should make the world economy work better.
二战后重建全球经济体系的那代人
The generation that rebuilt the global economy after the war
都可以看成是凯恩斯的孩子
really were children of Keynes.
但今天再读他  他的另一个观点的重要性不言而喻
But when you read him today, there's another equally powerful message that comes through,
经济生活的不确定性和不可预测性
about the great unpredictability, uncertainty, of economic life.
永远不要认为你已经度过了这个阶段  繁荣和衰退的对立已经结束
You should never think you¹ve got it covered, that you¹ve abolished boom and bust.
他们仍然是巨大的谜团
That¹s the great paradox.
凯恩斯一方面让经济学家们自信
The man who did most to make economists arrogant
他们可以按照自己的意愿改造世界
in their capacity to bend the world to their will,
另一方面也给出了自我怀疑的最好理由
also gave them or should have given them the best reasons for self-doubt.
下一时段的货币权力  凯恩斯最大的对手-哈耶克
Next time on the Power Of Money, Keynes' great adversary, Friedrich Hayek,
他从完全相反的角度看待同样的问题
who looked at the same facts and drew exactly the opposite view...
市场必须自由  政府应该减少干预
the market needed to be set free and government should back off.
公开大学已经制作了6集1分钟短片
The Open University has produced six one-minute animations
解释一些影响我们的经济观点
to explain some of the key economic ideas that affect all of us.
如果你想学习看不见的手或其他经济学秘密
So if you want to learn how to spot an invisible hand or other secrets of economics,
点击下列链接
Go to...
进入公开大学
And follow the link to the Open University.
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells http://UKsubtitles.ru.